professor Dave here, let's talk about titration
acid-base titration is a way of determining how much acid or base is present in solution by determining the
precise volume of acid or base that will
completely react with it. it's like a
kind of stoichiometry. on a titration
curve for an acidic solution, pH is
plotted against the volume of base that
is progressively added. as we add base
the pH slowly rises then sharply rises
towards the equivalence point. this is
the point where precisely enough base
has been added to neutralize the exact
amount of acid in solution. when we
perform titrations we recognize the
equivalence point by using something
called an indicator. this is a substance
that will turn a vivid color once the
equivalence point has been reached. when
we neutralize a strong acid with a
strong base the equivalence point will
be 7. if either or both species are
weak this number will vary. for example
let's say there's a solution of sodium
hydroxide and we want to know its
concentration. we react 3.0M sulfuric acid with 25 mL
of the base and we find that it takes 11.6 mL of
acid to reach the equivalence point. if
we convert to liters and then have
conversion factors for the concentration
of the acid and then the stoichiometric
ratio, we can arrive at the concentration
of the reactants. let's check
comprehension
thanks for watching subscribe to my
channel for more tutorials and as always
feel free to email me